My name is Michall Hussein. [music]
Gandhi touched my life and those of
hundreds of millions.
He was the Indian messiah who brought
the British Empire to its knees.
the activist who taught the world a new
way to make history.
He was the visionary who called for a
world without racial or religious
discrimination. The martyr who in 1948
at the age of 79 fell to an assassin's
bullet.
Internationally, Gandhi is revered as
the father of nonviolent struggle.
But I was brought up with a rather
different picture of Gandhi. My family
were Muslims in India at the time of
independence. They didn't feel that he
was a leader for them or understood the
fears they had about an independent
India dominated by Hindus. In the end,
they were among the millions who left
for the new state of Pakistan.
>> Gandhi's life is not what it seems.
We think we know this story of the
visionary in traditional dress, but what
of the gentleman barrista?
We know of Gandhi the vegetarian, but
what of the Gandhi who craved meat?
We know the pacifist, but what of the
Gandhi who put his faith in jihad?
I want to discover for myself the real
Gandhi, the man behind the Mahatma, the
human being behind the contradictions.
This is a man who in the final years of
his life said that people weren't
listening to him anymore, preferring to
just take his picture instead. I'd like
to find out more about what he was
saying and whether we should be
listening to him today.
Mumbai. I a chaotically modern
westernized city [music] at the sharp
end of India's thrusting economy whose
urban English-speaking middle classes
seem increasingly comfortable with the
new international religion consumerism.
What would Gandhi have made of all this?
I wonder. Is there still room for his
spiritual non-materialistic
nonviolent message in modernday Mumbai?
It's a piece of history that, you know,
we are very proud of. Uh, and that's
where it ends. I want to be rich. You
know, I want to make money. I want to be
successful. And I don't know whether
Gandhi [music] stood for that.
And yet, wherever you go in this city,
it seems Gandhi is looking down on you.
From statues, pictures, banknotes,
streets, and buildings bearing his name.
India seems to have a bit of a lovehate
relationship with its ursw leader.
Why?
To find out about the Indian prophet who
[music] preached truth and nonviolence.
I'm heading northwest to Porbandha in
the state of Gujarat where Mahandas
Karamchand Gandhi was born on October
the 2nd 1869.
He was born in an India very different
to today, a country wholly subservient
to the British Empire.
And the thriving fishing port of Poor
Bander was no exception.
Gandhi's birthplace still exists. A
surprise to discover that the future
leader of India's masses was born into a
fairly well-off middleclass family. His
father a senior civil servant working
for the government
was in this room exactly at this place
wearing the swastika
that that Gandhi was born. That's the
exact spot that Mahatma Gandhi was born
in. And um it was in this room that his
extraordinary life began.
>> In these beautiful rooms, there's no
real clue that they witnessed the
formative years of India's preeminent
spiritual and political leader. It's
only when you step into the courtyard of
the rather overblown adjoining Gandhi
memorial that the importance of these
early years is pulled into sharper
focus. specifically in the two words
engraved in the marble beneath his
portrait.
They are a himsa which means nonviolence
and satya which means truth. A himsa
underpins Hinduism's vegetarian
philosophy as in nonviolence towards
animals.
But it's also central to another Indian
faith, Janism. The Jane monks he would
have seen on the streets of Poor Bander
wore masks over their faces to avoid
inhaling and harming even the tiniest
creature. I met up with a local Jane
monk who told me that his commitment to
nonviolence is based on the right of all
beings to exist equally and the
commitment even extends to the equal
rights of all religions.
It was Gandhi's mother herself drawn to
Janism who first exposed her son to the
idea of nonviolence as the road to
spiritual and social equality.
Satya or truth is another Gandhian
principle a seed also planted in his
early years.
Gandhi himself records seeing a
traveling production of Haris Chandra,
the story of the truthful king who
refuses to deviate from the path of
truth.
But he pays a heavy price. He has to
leave his kingdom and his palaces. Worse
still, he loses his wife and son.
For his steadfastness, the gods offer
the king a place in heaven with his
family and all his subjects.
Gandhi writes in his autobiography that
the play affected him deeply. The idea
of truth as the path to eternal
salvation would stay with him for life.
>> [singing and music]
>> Gandhi's legacy in his hometown is
obvious. In recognition of its most
famous son, the whole state of Gujarat
is vegetarian and alcohol-free.
Though for some locals, even that's not
enough.
atma
and
>> I've been asking why he does this and he
says in not only in memory of Gandhi G
but also so [music] people in poor band
and all over the world will will
remember him
>> as a young school boy there was no hint
of the future holy man or freedom
fighter His horizon was limited like
that of most boys of his age. But I do
wonder if Gandhi would have become quite
as remarkable a man without the spirit
of adventure you breathe in a port like
Poor Bander.
Gandhi would have watched ships come and
go from here throughout his childhood.
He would have wondered what goods they
were bringing in and wondered where the
outgoing ships were destined for. He was
a child of a port city. the sea would
have been in his blood. And as a young
boy looking out on these waters, he must
have thought about what lay beyond them
and thought about the travels that he
might undertake in his own life.
For the moment, adventure was put on
hold as education took center stage and
a new element in Gandhi's makeup took
shape.
His spirit of rebellion.
Gandhi moved with his family here to
Rajkot where his father was state prime
minister and in 1880 at the age of 11 he
passed the entrance exam into this high
school where he was to be educated in
English.
He was an average student but he admits
in his own writing that he was easily
distracted in his early teens. The main
reason seems to have been his marriage
at the age of 13.
Her name was Casturba, a neighbor's
daughter from back in Porbander.
It wasn't unusual for boys to be married
so young. But Gandhi seems to have
become incredibly jealous, wondering
what his wife was getting up to while he
was stuck at school.
But what interests me is Gandhi's
defiant attitude [music] towards
authority and convention. He admits to
drinking, stealing, and surprisingly
eating meat.
>> He thought that the vegetarian diet of
his fellow countrymen had made them
feeble and that meat eating was the only
way to oust the ruling Brits. Why don't
we?
>> He had already.
>> According to Ushakant Manad, who looks
after the Gandhi house here in Rajkot,
this was typical of the boy.
>> You know, in his early days, he was a
very bad boy. As I said, he had taken
meat. He had taken wine. He had taken
womanizing, he had taken stolen gold
from his father's pocket. All these
vices were there in while he was living
here.
That's not to say the teenage Gandhi
didn't have a conscience. Far from it.
His vow to always tell the truth
compelled him to confess his crimes to
his father, who he records wept
silently.
And there were more signs that Gandhi
was a rebel with a conscience. In his
last years of high school, his father
fell seriously ill. Gandhi kept a
dutiful vigil at his bedside. rooms of
the family.
>> But one night, Mahandas crept from his
ailing father's room to make love to his
pregnant wife.
His father died during his absence.
It made a tremendous impression which he
later recorded in his autobiography.
I felt deeply ashamed and miserable. I
ran to my father's room. and I saw that
if animal passion had not blinded me, he
would have died in my arms.
He was 16 years old.
A few months later, the baby that
Kasurba was carrying died within a few
days of its birth. Gandhi viewed it as
divine retribution for deserting his
father in the moment of his death.
The incident colored his view of sex, of
his wife, even of his own imperfection.
But all that lay in the distant future,
Gandhi had yet to break out of Rajkot.
2 years after the death of his father
and the 18-year-old Gandhi was to leave
school and launch himself into the
world.
He felt claustrophobic at home. He
wanted an escape. An awkward child
looking for a place to fit in. A family
friend provided it. He suggested that
Gandhi should go to England to train to
be a lawyer.
Here was the chance to learn the nuts
and bolts of empire, the chance to play
the British at their own game. His
mother was reluctant to let him go. She
turned to her religion for guidance.
She gave him a necklace of beads made
from the sacred tulsi tree.
Wearing the necklace would protect him
while he was away. [music]
>> She then asked a Jane monk to witness
three promises she wanted her son to
make.
He administered the oath and I vowed not
to touch wine, woman and meat. This
done, my mother gave her permission.
At last, Gandhi [music]
was able to leave Rajkot for Bombay. But
before sailing, the aspiring lawyer had
one more hurdle to overcome.
He was called before the elders of his
cast, the merchant class, who denied him
permission to travel abroad.
And if he insisted on crossing the dark
waters to England, he would be
pronounced an outcast from his faith.
Gandhi [music] went anyway.
He left Bombay on the 4th of September
1888, a month before his 19th birthday.
The Indian Messiah in waiting had chosen
his personal advancement over his
religion.
He crossed these dark waters an outcast.
But against all his expectations, London
would awaken in the young Gandhi a
spiritual spark that his own country
could not.
As he approached Tilbury docks, there
were no [music] regrets, only ambition.
as he stepped ashore in his crisp white
linen suit. The height of that ambition
was to experience England and to
transform himself into an English
gentleman. He was ready to soak up what
London had to offer.
He was a rather shy young man. Um, but
he portrayed himself therefore very much
as a young Englishman. He he dressed in
court dress of the day with very western
clothes.
>> This is the place where Gandhi became a
lawyer, London's inner temple.
>> I was shown around by its sub treasurer,
Patrick Madams. British system of common
law. You couldn't practice law at the
time anywhere in the British Empire
unless you were attached to one of the
ins of court in London.
>> You can see his arrival here in 18 uh
uh8. You can see the 6th of November and
was admitted to the inn for a fee uh to
cover his threeear study of £140
11 shillings and 5. One of the reasons
he chose to come to the inner temple was
that our fees were higher than the other
ins and so therefore he concluded it
must be better. [laughter]
>> So he thought that was a very good
thing.
>> He thought that was a very good reason
indeed.
>> His time at the inner temple was to
leave an indelible mark on Gandhi not
just because of his studies but because
of what he ate.
>> So this is the dining hall and he would
have had to have his dinners here to
fulfill the requirement. It was a
requirement to be called to the bar that
you have 24 dinners a year. He was here
for three years, so that's 72 dinners.
>> It couldn't have been easy for him
though with being a vegetarian.
>> Well, it wasn't because he'd given this
undertaking to his mother that he would
abstain from alcohol and he would
abstain from meat. And I think there was
a general feeling in mid Victorian
polluted London that you couldn't
survive without alcohol and meat.
In fact, Gandhi was in real danger of
wasting away. He lived on boiled cabbage
in the temple dining rooms and bread and
jam in his lodgings.
He was not a vegetarian by conviction,
but he had made a promise to his mother.
And on [music] such little things,
history turns. For the decision to keep
this promise was of great consequence.
It began the transformation from
Victorian gentleman to reformer.
It reconnected him to Gujarat and it
gave those childhood notions of
nonviolence and truth a new purpose.
You might think that a foreign student
in late Victorian London might have
found it difficult to locate a
vegetarian hostelry. But looking at this
map, in fact, there were several places
catering to Gandhi's specific dietary
requirements.
His discovery of these vegetarian
establishments no doubt did him the
power of good. But their real
significance was in Gandhi's political
awakening. For at the time, [music]
vegetarian restaurants were at the heart
of London's lively and fashionable world
of reform. Tristram,
>> hello. I'm Michelle.
>> Tristramm Stewart is the author of a
history of vegetarianism.
>> This was really interesting to me that
there were several vegetarian
restaurants in this area at the time
that he lived.
>> The records suggest that there were up
to 34 in London in the 1880s. It's still
regarded as fairly cranky and extreme,
but there is a body of political
reformers who are involved in the
vegetarian movement. They see it as a
key, in fact, to reforming human nature
and human behavior. They regarded eating
meat and eating blood as the way in
which violence and aggression enters the
human body and influences the behavior.
>> So if everyone becomes a vegetarian, you
automatically start to have a more
gentle society.
>> That's absolutely right. That was
something that he picked up in London
from these radical social reforming
contemporaries.
>> And those ideas became so central to to
the way that we think of him today. One
has to wonder how how his thinking would
have been had he had he not encountered
this scene in London.
>> Well, precisely. We know that before he
came to London, he was actually
convinced that eating meat was a was a
key to making Indians strong and that
was the way of kicking out the British.
The exact reverse becomes the case. By
the time he's left London, he's
convinced that vegetarianism is the key
and nonviolence is the technique that he
is going to use to boot the British out
of India.
Gandhi got much more out of London than
he'd bargained for. He now [music]
understood vegetarianism in a social,
political, and ethical context, and how
closely related it was to a himsa,
nonviolence.
But London had yet more to offer. It was
here that Gandhi gained a new deeper
understanding [music]
of the childhood notion of satya truth.
It came from an unexpected religious
source.
Gandhi became [music] an active member
of the vegetarian society contributing
articles to its magazine. This
introduced him to the great and the good
of London society where he was exposed
to the leading reformers and the new
religious ideas of the day.
In Gandhi's old stomping ground in West
London, I met Katherine Tedri, an
authority on his defining influences.
She told me about a movement attracting
much attention in Gandhi's London, the
Theosophical Society and its founder one
Madame Blavvatzki.
>> She
thought that all the religions of the
world um were essentially different
versions of one fundamental underlying
religion like the perennial religion,
the perennial philosophy
>> and all that struck a chord with Gandhi
did it. He's very attracted by the idea
because um he could see um that Hinduism
was being taken seriously. It began to
make him think about the idea of
religions cross- fertilizing each other.
I think Madame Blavski uh took ideas
from Christianity as well as Hinduism.
She took ideas from all over the place
but particularly from Christianity and
Hinduism. And Gandhi began to see how
you might express religious ideas in in
different ways.
As [music] with vegetarianism, Gandhi
was rediscovering his own heritage
through western eyes. It stimulated a
thirst for spiritual knowledge for
ultimate truth. And it was here that he
read [music] two seinal texts from
Christian and Hindu scripture. The
sermon on the mount [music] and the
Bhagavad Gita.
He does say in his autobiography that
both these famous texts [music] are
about the same thing. They're about
renunciation as the route to liberation.
And I think the idea of renunciation as
a route to salvation was absolutely key
in understanding both his uh religious
development and his political tactics.
My young mind tried to unify the
teachings of the Gita and the sermon on
the mount.
That renunciation with the highest form
of religion appealed to me greatly.
In his own writings, Gandhi appears to
dismiss his student days as a preface, a
time before his life really began. But
there were seeds sewn here in London
that were to have a major impact on his
thinking and his actions in later life.
After his three years in London, Gandhi
is called to the bar. The young man from
Porband is a gentleman barristister.
And yet he's so much more. He's also an
idealist who begins to glimpse his
destiny as a force for good.
A destiny that nearly slipped through
his fingers on his return home.
Gandhi arrived back in India in July
1891, aged 22, fired up with ideas of
bringing about the spiritual and
political transformation of his
homeland.
But his optimism and joy at his
homecoming was short-lived. As soon as
his ship docked in Bombay, he received
the news of his mother's death.
His brothers told him of her dying wish
that he should be admitted back into his
cast.
He went on a pilgrimage to bathe in holy
waters to wipe away the stain of having
crossed the dark waters.
He returned to Rajkot to face the cast
elders. But Gandhi was told he would
always be an outcast.
It was a blow to his hopes of
reintegration.
And professionally, there was bad news,
too. His brother had become embroiled in
some shady dealings, and Gandhi
undertook to plead his case before the
British political agent. Armed with his
knowledge of the English rule of law,
Gandhi the barristister must have felt
confident. But the meeting was a
disaster.
The agent quickly warned the newly
qualified lawyer off the subject, but
Gandhi did not take the hint. He was
asked to leave, but persisted until a
servant was called to forcibly remove
him. It was total humiliation both
politically and professionally.
The incident compounded his isolation.
He now stood very little chance of
plying his trade in his hometown.
So when an offer came from a law firm in
South Africa, a position little above
that of a clock, he had no option. He
had to take it.
And that decision changed the course of
his life.
So once again Gandhi was leaving India.
He would have had plenty of time to
reflect on the long voyage. But unlike
the last time he left when he was full
of hope and ambition about going to
England, this time he was leaving after
experiencing both loss and failure at
home. It was a real low point. It was
unclear how he was ever going to
resuscitate his legal career and no sign
of the potential of this young man who
would one day be known all over the
world.
Gandhi [music] was 24. He sailed into
Durban Harbor, an outcast, a failure
rejected by both his religion [music]
and his chosen profession.
But he was to leave South Africa 21
years later with an international
reputation [music] big enough to return
to India as its savior. It would be a
[music] remarkable turnaround. But I
want to find out how
because by all accounts Gandhi's start
in South Africa couldn't have been
worse.
He stepped onto the docks in Durban,
having again put some thought to his
dress. A European style frock coat and a
turban of his own design. His English
gentleman's wings had been clipped. It
had made him think. A young lawyer
trained and refined in London, but
definitely perhaps even defiantly
Indian.
South Africa today boasts the largest
Indian community outside of Asia. Many
are descended from workers who came here
as virtual slaves on the sugar
plantations, railways, and coal mines
servicing the British Empire.
Others came from merchant families who
made their living from the trade between
the two continents.
Gandhi's new employer was one such
merchant. His name was Dada Abdullah. He
hired the young lawyer to help on a
disputed business claim.
Soon after his arrival, he brought
Gandhi here to Durban Magistrate's
Court. His first experience of the South
African legal system was not
particularly encouraging. He was asked
by the presiding magistrate to remove
his turban. He refused. I'm trying to
imagine what was going through Gandhi's
head on this crucial day, the very first
time that he ever appeared in the Durban
courthouse. There was a huge amount at
stake for him. This was a lastditch
attempt to resuscitate his legal career.
When he walked in, he had chosen to
adopt a very obvious symbol of his
Indian identity. But the judge told him
it was not appropriate. And rather than
defer to the authority of that judge in
this courtroom, he decided to take a
stand. Perhaps he was offended. Perhaps
he was angry. But in his reaction, there
was the sign of something we hadn't seen
before in his life.
>> An almost steelely selfbelief.
The Turban incident was Gandhi's first
recorded experience of color prejudice
South African style, but it was far from
being his last.
Dada Abdullah impressed with Gandhi's
stance against the colonial authorities
sent him to represent his dispute in
person. The journey was a turning point.
He boarded a train in Durban heading
north into the bore dominated Transfal
Republic and its capital Ptoria.
As he sat in his first class carriage
soaking up the spectacular landscapes,
he must have thought he'd finally
arrived.
How wrong he was. People in his carriage
began to stare and then complain to the
train staff. Gandhi produced a valid
first class ticket and made loud
protestations.
It was to no avail. He was asked to move
into a thirdass carriage and when he
refused, he was forcibly thrown off the
train.
To add insult to injury, he spent a
freezing night in the waiting room here
at Peter Merittsburg station. He wrote
in his autobiography,
>> "I began to think of my duty. Should I
fight for my rights or go back to India?
>> Or should I go on to Pritoria without
minding the insults and return to India
after finishing the case?"
>> The waiting room is now a place of
pilgrimage. David Genghan from the
Gandhi Memorial Committee explained why.
>> What do you feel when you're sitting in
this room?
Yeah, it's uh you you you you can't help
but feel moved at what transpired here
and u I tell the story so many times but
I I you you still get a lump in your
throat when you
>> when you kind of relate this. It was
right here in this waiting room where he
contemplated whether he should be going
back to India or stay and suffer this
kind of indignity. He realized that what
he experienced was perhaps a temporary
thing because he was a visitor, but
certainly people of his origin suffered
this kind of uh treatment on a daily
basis. And so there was a birthing that
happened here in this in this room.
>> I should try if possible to root out the
disease of color prejudice and suffer
hardships in the process. [music]
As [music] a direct result of the racial
abuse at Peter Marittsburg, Gandhi had
found a cause. A cause that stirred up
those [music] boyhood beliefs in truth
and equality. A cause to which he could
dedicate his [music] knowledge of
religion and the law. A cause that was
to occupy him for the next 21 years.
Within a week of arriving in Ptoria, he
was planning to set up a trade union of
Indian merchants.
But Gandhi could never be just a
politician or an activist. If London had
directed him towards the twin goals of
social and religious reform, it was
Ptoria that showed him how to achieve
them.
It was here that he realized the deeply
spiritual nature of his calling, one
that would inform everything he set his
mind to.
Fatima is a renowned anti-apartate
activist whose life's work has been the
fight against injustice and oppression.
She's written extensively about Gandhi's
life in South Africa and I asked her why
for him politics on its own wasn't
enough.
>> I think in himself he was born with a
sense of inner divinity.
>> Are you saying that he thought he was
divine?
>> No. He was too humble all his life to
ever think of him of himself as divine.
But the central
content of the human was the soul and
the soul was divine. Do you think that
he thought he was special that he was
destined for something? He came to that
realization
particularly
at the Marsburg
station when he was kicked off the train
and when he sat there in that cold night
thinking
>> was that the moment that set him on the
path to being the Mahatma?
>> I think so. Gandhi was never simply a
political being. The fight had to be
divine. It had to be moral.
>> Gandhi was ready to take his place in
South African politics, but not just as
a lawyer and campaigner for the rights
of his fellow Indians. He was entering
the fry as their moral leader.
This is a picture of the young Gandhi
that hints at the future great soul and
savior of India.
Then an opportunity presented itself to
realize his destiny on a national scale.
It was a battle that was to occupy him
for his remaining time in Africa. A
battle that [music] would define him in
the eyes of the world as the charismatic
leader whose distinctive [music] and
decisive weapon was nonviolence.
>> [music]
>> The battle headquarters was to be
Johannesburg.
The battle that presented itself was the
Black Act of 1906.
The act required all Asians over the age
of 8 [music] to carry ID cards,
including fingerprints of all 10 digits.
It was a [music] deliberate attack on
their dignity and their rights. As
Gandhi pointed out, fingerprinting was
only used for identifying criminals.
Gandhi had no doubts that the black act
had to be resisted.
The [music] question was how?
This was the question that would [music]
finally give birth, shape, and form to
his trademark, nonviolent civil
disobedience.
And the [music] answers came flooding in
from his past.
Satya and Aimsa, the twin mantras of his
childhood.
These ideas came together to create
[music] one of the most original and
potent forms of political struggle in
history. He named [music] his approach
Satya Graha. Satya truth. Graa force.
Truth force.
Only nonviolent resistance would
generate enough divine power, enough
truth to defeat the oppressor. Only one
agonizing question remained for Gandhi.
How far should he should everyone go for
nonviolence?
Now at the age of 37, a new
controversial but decisive religious
idea entered the mix.
It came from Islam through Gandhi's
mainly Muslim merchant allies.
Fatamir thinks that it's at this point
in Johannesburg that Satyagraha is fully
and truly born.
>> He learned a great deal about Islam
here.
And you know it is interesting but if
you trace
the foundation
of satyagraha
you'll find that it is actually
influenced by jihad. I think followers
of of Gandhi today might be intrigued
and and perhaps upset even that you
would link Satya Graa with jihad which
is such a controversial term.
>> Absolutely correct. They are upset. But
the meaning of jihad is that you feel so
strongly about something
that you will commit to it
to the extent of dying for it.
So this is the literal
feeling in jihad.
Better to die than submit to such a law.
But how to die?
What should we dare to do so that there
would be [music] nothing before us
except a choice between victory or
death?
Energized by jihad, Gandhi organized,
galvanized and inspired his merchant
friends to put Satya Graa fullcale
passive resistance to the test.
On the 11th of September 1906, a pledge
to defy the Black Act was taken in
Johannesburg.
At the heart of it was a solemn oath to
go to jail rather than submit to such a
law.
The tactic worked like a dream. The act
required all Indians to register [music]
by the end of November 1907.
When the date arrived, only 545
out of a possible 7,000 had done so. As
he expected, by the end of January 1908,
Gandhi and another 2,000 people had been
thrown into jail.
Success was in sight, but somehow Gandhi
managed to snatch defeat from the jaws
of victory.
The harsh conditions in Johannesburg's
infamous Fort Prison soon began to
weaken the resolve of the merchants. The
colonial secretary of the transfmutz
sent an emissary here to negotiate with
Gandhi.
They agreed to a compromise, register
voluntarily and then smuts would repeal
the black act.
Gandhi's supporters naturally wondered
why they'd gone to jail if they now had
to register anyway.
It was a humiliating climbown.
Gandhi's career as a political leader
was nearly over before it had truly
begun.
When he was released from jail, an
outraged member of his own community
attacked him with an iron bar. Gandhi
nearly lost his life. But a friend, a
fellow inmate from Fort Prison, threw
himself over Gandhi, taking the blows
himself. The friend was Tambi Naidu.
Tambi didn't just save Gandhi's life. He
was also to save his reputation and
relaunch Gandhi's campaign.
Part of the fort is now a Gandhi museum.
My guide Prima Naidu is a celebrated
activist who was himself incarcerated
here. He is Tambi's grandson.
>> Something that Gandhi also did in
>> PMA explained how his grandfather told
Gandhi to broaden his campaign beyond
the merchant class. the working-class
people. Not only did they have numbers
on their side, uh, but they also brought
with them a kind of militancy to a pass
of resistance movement. Not militancy in
the sense that they took up arms or
something, but people who weren't afraid
to go to jail. It was often said that
people from the workingclass community
had nothing to lose but their chains
and so they joined the movement in huge
numbers. How important was it to
Gandhi's success that his following
widened in this way?
>> Uh well I think it had a huge impact on
his stature. You know when Mandela on
his first trip to uh to India they said
to the Indian officials that you gave us
Gandhi and we gave you a Mahatma and I
think that was a real the creating of a
Mahatma was in South Africa.
>> [music]
>> In 1913, Gandhi announced the resumption
of Satya Graha, a strike against [music]
a punitive tax.
The merchants didn't respond to his
call, but Gandhi had the laboring Indian
poor to call on now.
The strike had an immediate economic
[music] impact. It began in the coal
mines of Natal and spread quickly to the
railways and sugar estates.
But Gandhi, the master tactician, could
also see the political impact of the
strike.
[music] You see, many Indian laborers
lived in compounds provided by their
employers. If they went on strike, they
lost their [music] home. Gandhi's plan
was to flood the roads of Natal with
people.
[music]
He then promised to house the homeless
workers and their families on a farm
across the border [music]
between Natal and Transfal.
This was illegal. The border crossings
would inevitably provoke mass [music]
arrests.
The jails would be swamped. More
visibility, [music] more publicity, more
pressure on the authorities.
Charles Town on the Natal side of the
border with the Transval.
It was from here on the 6th of November
1913 at 6:30 a.m. and with the world's
press watching that Gandhi led 2,221
men, women, and children across the
border.
The response was brutal. Gandhi was
arrested and sentenced to 9 months
imprisonment.
The marchers were deported back to
Natal, but the strike spread. Soon the
papers were full of reports of Indians
incarcerated in mine shafts and other
brutalities.
The media outcry turned Gandhi into an
international figure of some standing
while fatally weakening Smutz and the
government. They had to cave in. The
divisive tax was repealed.
[music]
Gandhi had won.
The timid boy from poor Bandar was on
the threshold of realizing his destiny.
What a huge achievement this
represented. Satya Graha had gone from
being a passive idealistic niche idea to
one of immense power. Gandhi had managed
to mobilize thousands of people to unite
them under his leadership in pursuit of
a common cause. And for him it was to
mean recognition far beyond the borders
of South Africa.
When Gandhi returned to Durban, he was
treated as a hero. But his mind was
already elsewhere. He had accepted
[music] and fulfilled his destiny on
South African soil. Now India was
calling him home.
On July the 18th, 1914, he set sail
secure in the knowledge as he told his
supporters that a new force had arisen
in the world. The force of truth.
A new force had arisen in the world and
its name was Mahandas Karamchand Gandhi.
As Smarts commented when the future
Mahatma finally left for India, the
saint has left our shores. I sincerely
hope forever.
On the next stage of my journey, I
travel to India where I discover that
within 10 years of his return, Gandhi is
a spent force. So, how did he become the
father of the nation?